你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到Pwn学院
welcome to Pwn College
我是Yan
I'm Yan and
我们快到了汇编课的尾声
we are approaching the end of the assembly crash course
现在我们来谈谈
now we're going to talk about
如何编译我们的汇编器
how to actually build our assembly programs
以及实操
and play around with them
汇编被称为汇编
so recall assembly is called assembly
因为它是由汇编器汇编成二进制代码的
because it is assembled by an assembler into binary code
为了
in order to
构建我们之前讨论过的程序
build the program that we talked about previously
那个quit
that quits
这个程序就干这一件事（退出）
that's all this program does
我们得把它写进文件里
we have to write it into a file
汇编它
assemble it
然后我们就可以运行它
and then we can run it
写入文件时，需要做的一件事是
one thing we need to do to write into a file
告诉汇编器，我们使用的是什么语法
is tell the assembler what syntax we're using
我提到过AT&T
I mentioned AT&T
它是一个不好的汇编语法
broke everything by introducing a really bad assembly syntax
我们告诉汇编器，我们用英特尔语法
we're telling the assembler hey we're using the Intel syntax
然后还有
and then also
如果你想非常准确地区分
if you want to be extremely explicit
什么是寄存器，什么是变量名
with what is a register versus what is named variables
你可以在所有寄存器前加上百分号
you can prefix all your registers with percents
这看起来很蠢
that looks dumb
不蠢
I'm sure it doesn't look dumb
但出于我们的目的，有点傻
but it's silly for our purposes
我们不加百分号前缀
we just put no prefix here
现在我们可以编写程序了
now we can write our program
非常好
perfectly fine
井号后的内容都是注释
anything after a hash is a comment
注释中你可以写任何东西
you can write whatever there
现在好了
all right now
我们用汇编器
we grab our assembler
我们实际上使用整个编译套件
what we're actually gonna grab is the full compiler suite
因为它知道该怎么做
because it knows what to figure out
它会帮我们汇编
it'll assemble things for us
我们直接用gcc
we just call GCC
传一个-nostdlib参数
pass it -nostdlib
它表示
what this says is hey
这不是一个使用C库的C程序
this isn't a C program that uses C libraries
不要链接别的库
don't put other libraries in here
因为它们没用
because they won't work
它们想要一个C程序，不是你要给的
they expect different things from a C program than you're going to give them
就目前而言
in this for now
我的意思是，以后它们会派上用场
I mean of course later on they can work
写入二进制的elf文件quitter
write it to the binary the elf file quitter
这是我的源代码文件 quitter.s
and then here is my source code quitter.s
它向告警
it complains at you
它会告诉你
it's going to tell you
找不到某些符号
I can't find some symbol
但是没关系
but it's fine
能用
it still works
它会猜测程序的入口
it guesses where the start of the program is
它猜就是第一行
just it's going to guess it's the first line
这正合我意
which is perfect for you
然后生成了一个你可以执行的二进制文件
and then that produces a binary file that you can then execute
如果你反感这个警告
if this warning annoys you
你可以解决它
you can get rid of it
只需让代码稍微复杂一点
by making your assembly file a little bit more complicated
把这个放在开头
by putting this at the beginning
你说
you say hey
会有一个地方
there's going to be a location
它定义了从哪里开始执行
there's going to be a location that defines where to start execution
然后，嘿，它在这里
and hey here it is
这就是那个地方
here's the location
就像跳转标签一样
just like any other jump label
你可以这样做，以避免警告
you can do that to avoid that warning if it annoys you
这样，你就构建好了你的首个汇编程序
just like that you've built your first assembly program
你已经汇编了第一个汇编程序
you've assembled your first assembly program
怎么运行它
how do you run it
和其他程序一样
like any other program
./quitter
它就会退出
and it's just gonna quit
它会返回错误码
it's gonna return error code
会返回42
return code 42 out of the program
它就是给exit系统调用的参数
that's the argument to the exit syscall
你可以用特殊变量——问号
and you can use the special question Mark variable
在bash中查看它
to view it in bash
它会成功的
and it's gonna work
酷
awesome
你也可以反汇编
you can also get the assembly back out
以确保
to make sure
汇编的正常
I mean that it properly assembled
但也有其他情况
but there are other cases
比如阅读你没有汇编的程序的汇编
like reading the assembly of programs that you didn't assemble
你可以用objdump来反汇编程序
you can disassemble a program using objdump
你告诉objdump，我讨厌看AT&T语法
so you tell objdump hey I hate reading AT&T syntax
很不幸，AT&T是默认的
that's the default unfortunately very unfortunately
让它用Intel语法显示quitter的反汇编结果
say give me the Intel disassembly syntax of the quitter program
就是这个
and here it is
这是quitter程序
here is your quitter program
这是汇编指令
this is the assembly instructions
这些是
these are
这是42的十六进制值
this is 42 in Hex
这是60的十六进制值
this is 60 in Hex
这是exit的系统调用号
this is the syscall number for exit
这是exit的第一个参数
and this is the first argument to exit
然后是syscall
and then syscall boom
就是这样，超级简单
that's all it's super simple
这是这些指令的二进制表示
this is the binary representation of these instructions
这太酷了
how cool is that
这个2a，能在这里看见
so this 2a is going to actually be visible right here
你把它赋值给rdi
it's you're moving it into RDI
为什么它是32位的
and why is it a 32 bit number
不管怎样，这个2a 00 00 00是一个32位的值
anyways this 2a 00 00 00 is a 32 bit value
编码在
encoded in
不，我还是没明白
no I still didn't get it
用小端序存储
okay stored in little endian
这是3c 00 00 00
and here's your 3c 00 00 00
酷
cool
这表示赋值给rax
and this says move to rax
这表示赋值给rdi
this says move to rdi
这个0f 05是syscall指令
and this 0f 05 is the syscall instruction
现在你有了一个程序
and now you have a program alright
你也可以
you can also
这个新创建的ELF文件
so this ELF file that was created
这个quitter文件
this quitter file
我相信你看了前面关于ELF文件的课程
I'm sure you watch the lectures on ELF files in prior modules
这是一个大文件
it's a big file
它包含了所有其他的元数据
it's got like all of this other metadata
如果我们只想要这些字节呢
what if we just want these bytes
例如，如果你只想要这些字节
for example if you just want these bytes
这样你就可以把它们提交给
so that you can submit them to the
PWN学院汇编习题的评分脚本
the kind of grading script of the assembly practice problems on pwn college
你可以用这个命令把它们弄出来
well you can get them out using this weird command
objcopy能导出.text段
objcopy say dump the section .text
.text是ELF的一个部分
if you remember .text is a section of ELF
里面是你的二进制代码
where your binary code is
把它从这个elf文件，导入这个文件
dump it into this file from this elf
你这样做
and you just do it
就能拿到这些字节
so we have these bytes
我们导出它
we dump it
然后我们可以用hexdump查看这个文件
and then we can hexdump that file
我们能看到只有这些字节
we see it's just the bytes
很酷吧
pretty cool huh
然后你可以把它交给评分脚本
and then you can pass that to the grading script
你就准备好了
and you're good to go
对于二进制文件的习题，你已经准备好了
to the challenge of binaries and you're good to go
当然，你肯定会写出bug
of course you're going to introduce bugs
毫无疑问，你的代码将会有bug
there's no doubt that your code is going to be buggy
Ada Lovelace
1843年最早的计算机程序员之一
one of the original computer programmers in 1843
谈论过软件
talked about softwares
托马斯·爱迪生在1878年就提过bug（虫子）
Thomas Edison in 1878 was already talking about bugs
用来指代错误
right to mean a errors
当然还有在电脑里发现的著名飞蛾
and of course there's the famous moth found in a computer
在
in
我忘了具体日期
well I forgot the date
我想说的是在1948年
1948 I want to say
总之
anyways
大致是一个真正的虫子引发了软件错误
that's like an actual bug causing a software fault but
或者像这个例中，导致硬件故障
or causing a hardware fault in this case
bug这个词是相当古老的
but the term bugs is quite old
你的程序中也会有bug
and you will have bugs in your program
你需要调试它们
and you will need to debug them
如何调试它们
how do you debug them
调试是用调试器完成的
well debugging is done with debuggers
有专门的工具
specific special tools for this
比如GDB
such as GDB
GDB会添加一个断点
GDB will add a break point
中断你的程序
interrupt your program
方便你检查
and let you look around
这是什么原理
how does this work
这很有趣
well it's pretty interesting
在x86中有一个特殊的指令
there's a special instruction in x86
它说：嘿，我是个断点
that says hey I'm a break point
调试器
debugger
我是一个断点
I'm a break point
你可以把它插入你的代码中
and you can just insert it into your code
只需要插入这个int 3指令
you just insert this int 3 instruction
这是3号中断
that's interrupt 3
这就是断点中断
that's the break point interrupt
总之
anyways
你只需将它插入到代码中
you just insert it into your code
如果附加了调试器
if you have debugger attached
它能停止程序
it will helpfully stop the program
并允许你检查程序状态
and allow you to inspect its state
如果没有附加调试器
now if no debuggers attached
你的进程将终止
your process is gonna die
因为这不应该发生
because that shouldn't happen and
基本上操作系统会说：哇哦
basically the operating system says whoa ho
出乎意料了
this is not expected
我们要结束这一切
we're just gonna shut this whole situation
关闭进程
shut the process down
调试器也可以设置断点
so the debugger can also set break points
可以用调试器设置断点
you can set break points from a debugger
如果你用过调试器，你就知道这一点
if you ever use a debugger you know this
它的工作原理是这样的
but this is how it works
默认情况下
by default
它会查看你设置断点的地址
it just looks at the address you're setting a debugger at
并用INT 3指令替换那里的指令
and replaces the instruction there with an INT 3 instruction
当要执行原来的指令时
and when that instruction is actually hit
在后台
then in the background
调试器会说：好吧
the debugger just says okay
我们把原来的指令放回去
well let's put the old instruction back
然后执行这条指令
and execute just that instruction
再把它换回int 3
and then swap it back with the int 3
这就是调试器的工作原理
so this is actually how the debugger works
在pwn学院的汇编习题环境中
now specifically in the Assembly Crash Course challenges in pwn College
我们提供了一个自动化的调试器
we provide an automated debugger for you
只要你的代码在题中调用int 3
anytime your code calls int 3 in the challenge
就会输出一些有用的程序状态
we're going to give you a helpful printing of the program state
然后暂停，直到你按回车键
and pause until you hit enter
希望这能让调试更简单
that hopefully will make it easier
暂时不用学像GDB这样的调试器了
you don't have to learn how to use a debugger like GDB yet
暂时帮一下你
will hold your hand for now
但还是要学gdb
but you will need to learn gdb
你还需要使用strace
you also need to use strace
一个非常有用的调试工具
very helpful debugging tool
strace会运行你的程序
strace will actually run your program
当然
of course
要知道如何使用Strace
to know how to use Strace
可以查看man手册
look at the man page
strace会运行你的程序
Strace will run your program
并打印出它调用的每个系统调用
and will just print out every system call that it makes
用了哪些参数
what the arguments of it were
返回值是多少
and what the result was
对调试非常有用
super useful for debugging
应该是首选
should be your first attempt
甚至在GDB之前
maybe even before GDB
先用strace
strace first
如果用它搞不定
if you can't figure out from there
再GDB
GDB it
其他有用的工具
other useful tools
rappel，我之前提过它
rappel I mentioned it before
它能让你探索有效的指令
it allows you to explore effective instructions
去看看它
check it out
它已经装在dojo里了
it's in the dojo already
直接执行rappel
just run rappel
x86有广泛的文档记录
and x86 is widely documented
如果你想知道什么
if you want to know anything
这是最后的选择
this is the nuclear option
由英特尔创建的架构手册
the Architecture Manual created by Intel
这能有几千页
this is like thousands of pages long
这个felixcloutier维护着一个指令清单
this felixcloutier maintains an instruction listing
很好，能点击查看
very nice clickable
这里有每条x86指令的参考文档
and then here is a reference of every x86 instruction
包含它的字节码等等
and its byte encodings and so forth
对以后的模块非常有用
very useful for later modules
感谢你们跟随我踏上这个汇编之旅
thank you for following me on this Assembly journey
希望你学到了很多东西
I hope that you have Learned an enormous amount
我对汇编感到超级兴奋
and i am super excited about Assembly
记住，它是最正统的编程语言
remember it's the truest programming language
最简单的编程语言
the simplest programming language
甚至可能是最有趣的编程语言
and maybe even the funniest programming language
现在去dojo（道场）
now go to the dojo
做题吧，祝你好运
tackle those challenges and good luck